[Music]
hello everyone and welcome back to our
channel
in today's session we will be talking
about the most brimming topic of the r
the recommendation engine and how it
works
without wasting any more time let's
quickly jump into this video
what do you think when the word
recommendation comes to your mind
imagine a scenario where one of your
closest friends recommends you to watch
money heist on netflix or your sister
wants you to watch friends and your
mother wants you to spend some time
watching a planet documentary
are these recommendations based upon
what they like or what you like
the question is pretty relevant however
what if there is someone who understands
your choice and recommends something you
want to watch
well that's today's topic recommendation
engine
before we start our today's discussion
make sure you hit the subscribe button
to keep receiving notifications for our
master classes interview preparation
videos and so much more
here's everything you need to know about
recommendation engine
what is a recommender system
in today's digital world where people
spend most of their time watching
netflix or amazon prime the
recommendation system is the most potent
marketing tool a recommender system is
nothing fancy but an automated
information filtering system to filter
some entities composed of machine
learning and ai algorithm which predicts
what the customer wants to see
these entities can be any possible
products such as ads movies tv shows
songs and so on which we see on apps
like netflix amazon and youtube on every
day
today the e-commerce space is loaded
with information with hundreds of movies
and shows released every day a
recommendation system helps tackle this
challenge and saves customers a lot of
time while browsing the internet
the recommendation system automatically
directs the user to the product they
will mainly like
now let us understand this via example
say we watched a movie today and then
later we got recommendations for some
different movies based on previous
viewing history
other than movies it could also be a
product that we bought and then we get a
recommendation for a similar product
based on the power of previous viewing
history
note the recommender system not only
works in what products are being shown
but also in what order the products are
being ranked
the idea of a recommendation engine is
not new it is something you are already
familiar with
excited to know
do you watch movies on netflix or spend
time shopping on amazon or follow the
recommendation made by youtube for music
if yes you are already supporting the
recommendation system in many aspects
unknowingly which enhances your online
experience
now when you have understood
recommendation system it is important to
understand why the recommender system is
built
without any further ado let's see why
this is important
imagine what if you are left on netflix
between tons of movies to find your
favorite one or on youtube to find which
song you like the most it will be a
brainstorming session
that's exactly why recommendation engine
is important
businesses are showing us recommendation
and relevant content for a couple of
reasons for one most companies think
they understand their customer but often
customers can behave much differently
than businesses you ever think as their
choice fluctuate with time
so it's important to show the users what
is relevant to them and match their
choices while also sharing new content
which might grab their attention
as mentioned earlier the internet is
flooded with good content
therefore you need a tool that
bifurcates your choices from the hoard
of information present on the internet
today the recommendation system serves
to help us solve the information
overload problem and helps us narrow
down the set of choices
it helps businesses sell more relevant
content that might attract users and
make them stick forever
from the customer's perspective the
recommender system helps save valuable
time and showcases what interests the
user
however from a business perspective it
helps to understand better what the user
wants and might want in the near future
so how does the recommendation engine
work
now when you have understood exactly
what the recommendation engine is and
why it is necessary today let us
understand how it works how does the
recommender system work
imagine you like your pizza with tomato
toppings how does your mom know that you
like tomatoes on your pizza
the best and the easiest way is that she
could have asked you specifically if you
want tomatoes or she must have washed
you from a distance while ordering
pizzas a recommended engine is nothing
different instead it almost works the
same way
it will either ask you what you
preferred or see what kind of content
you are regularly watching
say you like family shows then it will
mostly recommend similar content which
will hook you to watch more and even if
your mom knows you well maybe a machine
learning algorithm knows your choices
even better
for example when you go to netflix or
any other services which are mostly
based on recommendation the first time
you go there they ask you what your
taste buds are
whether you prefer horror shows or
comedy series have you ever thought the
reason behind this
well it's to understand what the user
may like and recommend the same to grab
the interest in the very first go as
they are completely clueless about your
choice as they have never interacted
with you personally or digitally
for any service you are a valuable asset
therefore they are bound to be treated
like king and queens
it's called the cold start problem where
they have no idea of who you are and
have no profile for you therefore they
will force you to at least put in
something say what movies you like what
are your food choices what singer you
must love the most what genre grabs your
attention because how will they know
otherwise
let us understand how youtube
recommendations work
youtube videos are mainly dependent on
three factors
watch time videos that have a lot of
watch time then engagement and finally
topic relevance which means the video is
relevant to topic i am looking for
another factor that plays a vital role
in video recommendation is the user's
history
say you continuously watch a particular
youtube channel you will regularly
recommend videos of them and content
similar to theirs
if i watch a trailer of avengers end
game the stakes are high that i'll
recommend the trailer of iron man or
behind the scenes of avengers endgame
note these algorithms are supremely
smart which know what to show you when
and they can be highly accurate
it should also be noted that there are
higher chances that each company
including youtube or amazon might have
its own recommendation engines or a
specific way of generating
recommendations as one company's method
of recommendation might not apply to
another company or all
what are the different types of
recommendation engine
before understanding how the netflix and
amazon recommendation engine works it is
important to understand the different
types of recommendation engines
broadly the recommendation engines are
divided into two parts collaborative
filtering collaborative filtering is a
type of recommendation engine which
majorly focuses on understanding and
analyzing the customer's behavior
preferences or activities to suggest
reliable product or services
you're a large part of information is
collected depending on a customer
preference to see what the customer
might like
amazon is one of the biggest examples of
collaborative filtering as it works on
collecting preferences from distinct
sources
techniques involved in collaborative
filtering non-probabilistic algorithm
user based nearest neighbor item-based
nearest neighbor
reducing dimensionality
next up probabilistic algorithm
bcn network model em algorithm content
based system the content based system
deals with the idea of if you like a
particular product you will like the
similar products too here the machine
learning algorithm suggests products
that are similar to the user's history
for example if a person likes horror
movies the system will recommend movies
from the same genre repeatedly how does
netflix recommendation work
the success of netflix is mostly
dependent on the recommendation engine
whatever they do is based upon what the
recommendation engine suggests
record says 80 of people who play on
netflix comes from netflix
recommendation algorithm so it's really
big level for netflix
in a world where there are so many
cultures and people with different
tastes it's hard to please everyone at
the right time with the right content
and that's where recommendation engine
enters
here is the science behind netflix
whenever you click on the netflix tab
the recommendation system gets ready to
direct you to the right source of
information you might be looking for
netflix estimates your action based upon
your number of factors including your
interaction with the services say your
search history or your most recently
watched showed other members who have
similar taste or presence as of you
information about the title such as the
genre you most likely to watch in actors
you love the most categories and so on
in addition to know what you love
watching on netflix they personalize
your experience based upon the time you
watch netflix the device on which you
are watching netflix for how long you
are watching netflix in the entire day
or one sitting
all these pieces of data may not matter
to you however they are most important
source of information by which netflix
knows you better than everyone
when you create your profile on netflix
for very first time you must have
noticed that netflix asks you to choose
a title you prefer over others once you
start to select the options the netflix
recommendation engine starts to
bifurcate your choices and presents you
with everything you would want to watch
apart from netflix another platform that
is gaining immense popularity these days
is amazon
let's discuss how amazon recommendation
engine works
how does the amazon recommendation
engine work
amazon being a multi-billion dollar
estate many emerging companies look up
to amazon and its magic ingredient which
made it the world's most visited
e-commerce website till now
note amazon heavily believes in data
driven marketing
if you see something that you like and
something pops up that matches your
preferences understand the
recommendation engine is working at its
best and throwing some great results
the choice you make on amazon are based
upon three significant factors including
events rating and filtering
let's start with events
amazon stores and tracks data on all
custom behavior and activity on the site
every time you search something on the
search bar say you type laptop a record
of the event is locked in the database
and the entry is stored as something
like user a clicked on x product whether
you like a product add a product to the
cart or purchase a product your actions
are captured which promotes future
purchases
next on the list is ratings ratings are
an essential component of every
e-commerce website including amazon
because it unveils how the customer
feels about the particular product here
the maximum rating is 5 star so in case
the user truly loves the product he can
easily give it a 5 star the last in the
list is filtering filtering products are
based upon rating and other user data
amazon recommendation engine use three
types of filtering collaborative
user-based and hybrid approach let's
discuss each of these collaborative
filtering in collaborative filtering the
visitors choices are compared to each
other and based upon that they are
recommended the most suitable product
user based filtering the second one is
user based filtering in which users
browser history cart item purchases and
likes a significant role before
providing recommendations
with this we come to the end of our
session now that you have learnt what
the recommendation engine is and its
functioning we would love to hear your
views about the same in the comment
section below if you guys have any
queries or questions about what we just
discussed you can leave them in the
comment section and we will get back to
you
before leaving let's quickly have a
summary of what we discussed today we
started our today's discussion with the
recommendation engine where we
understood the ai algorithm through an
example
then we briefly discussed why the
recommendation engine is so important
later we talked about how it works and
various aspects which are taken into
consideration
in the end we also discuss the amazon
and netflix recommendation engine works
if you like this video don't forget to
hit the like button share and subscribe
to our channel don't forget to press the
bell icon to be notified every time we
upload a video we will see you next time
bye