Hello, everyone.
This is Atul from Edureka
and welcome to today's topic
of discussion on
AI vs Machine Learning
vs Deep Learning.
These are the term
which have confused a lot
of people and if you
too are one among them,
let me resolve it for you.
Well artificial intelligence
is a broader umbrella
under which machine learning
and deep learning come you
can also see in the diagram
that even deep learning is
a subset of machine learning
so you can say
that all three of them
the AI the machine learning
and deep learning are just
the subset of each other.
So let's move on and understand
how exactly the differ
from each other.
So let's start
with artificial intelligence.
The term artificial intelligence
was first coined
in the year 1956.
The concept is pretty old,
but it has gained
its popularity recently.
But why well,
the reason is earlier we had
very small amount of data
the data we had Was not enough
to predict the accurate result,
but now there's a tremendous
increase in the amount
of data statistics suggest
that by 2020 the accumulated
volume of data will increase
from 4.4 zettabyte stew
roughly around 44 zettabytes
or 44 trillion GBs
of data along with such
enormous amount of data.
Now, we have more
advanced algorithm
and high-end computing
power and storage
that can deal with such large
amount of data as a result.
It is expected
that 70% of Enterprise
will Implement ai
over the next 12 months
which is up from 40 percent
in 2016 and 51 percent in 2017.
Just for your understanding
what does AI well,
it's nothing but a technique
that enables the machine to act
like humans by replicating
the behavior and nature
with AI it is possible
for machine to learn
from the experience.
The machines are just
the responses based
on new input there
by performing human-like tasks.
Artificial intelligence can
be trained to accomplish
specific tasks by processing
large amount of data
and recognizing pattern in them.
You can consider
that building an artificial
intelligence is like Building
a Church, the first church
took generations to finish.
So most of the workers
were working in it never saw
the final outcome those working
on it took pride
in their craft building bricks
and chiseling stone
that was going to be placed
into the great structure.
So as AI researchers,
we should think of ourselves
as humble brick makers
whose job is to study
how to build components
example Parts is planners
or learning algorithm
or accept anything
that someday someone
and somewhere will integrate
into the intelligent systems
some of the examples
of artificial intelligence
from our day-to-day life
our Apple series just playing
computer Tesla self-driving car
and many more these examples
are based on deep learning
and natural language processing.
Well, this was about what is AI
and how it gains its hype.
So moving on ahead.
Let's discuss about machine
learning and see what it is
and white pros of an introduced.
Well Machine learning came
into existence in the late 80s
and the early 90s,
but what were the issues
with the people
which made the machine learning
come into existence?
Let us discuss them one by one
in the field of Statistics.
The problem was
how to efficiently train
large complex model
in the field of computer science
and artificial intelligence.
The problem was how to train
more robust version of AI system
while in the case
of Neuroscience problem
faced by the researchers was
how to design operation
model of the brain.
So these are some of the issues
which had the largest influence
and led to the existence
of the machine learning.
Now this machine learning
shifted its focus
from the symbolic approaches.
It had inherited
from the AI and move
towards the methods and model.
It had borrowed from statistics
and probability Theory.
So let's proceed and see
what exactly is
machine learning.
Well Machine learning
is a subset of AI
which The computer to act
and make data-driven decisions
to carry out a certain task.
These programs are algorithms
are designed in a way
that they can learn
and improve over time
when exposed to new data.
Let's see an example
of machine learning.
Let's say you want
to create a system
which tells the expected weight
of a person based on its side.
The first thing you do
is you collect the data.
Let's see there is
how your data looks
like now each point
on the graph represent
one data point to start
with we can draw a simple line
to predict the weight
based on the height.
For example, a simple line
W equal x minus hundred
where W is waiting kgs
and edges hide
and centimeter this line can
help us to make the prediction.
Our main goal is
to reduce the difference
between the estimated value
and the actual value.
So in order to achieve it we
try to draw a straight line
that fits through all
these different points
and minimize the error.
So our main goal is
to minimize the error
and make them as small as
possible decreasing the error
or the difference
between In the actual value
and estimated value
increases the performance
of the model further
on the more data points.
We collect the better.
Our model will become we
can also improve our model
by adding more variables
and creating different
production lines for them.
Once the line is created.
So from the next time
if we feed a new data,
for example height
of a person to the model,
it would easily predict the data
for you and it will tell you
what has predicted
weight could be.
I hope you got
a clear understanding
of machine learning.
So moving on ahead.
Let's learn about deep learning.
Now what is deep learning?
You can consider deep learning
model as a rocket engine
and its fuel is
its huge amount of data
that we feed to
these algorithms the concept
of deep learning is not new,
but recently it's hype as
increase and deep learning
is getting more attention.
This field is a particular kind
of machine learning
that is inspired by
the functionality of
our brain cells called neurons
which led to the concept
of artificial neural network.
It simply takes
the data connection between all
the artificial neurons
and adjust them according
to the data pattern more neurons
are added at the size
of the data is large
it automatically features
learning at multiple
levels of abstraction.
Thereby allowing a system
to learn complex function
mapping without depending
on any specific algorithm.
You know,
what no one actually
knows what happens
inside a neural network
and why it works so well,
so currently you can call
it as a black box.
Let us discuss some
of the example of deep learning
and understand it
in a better way.
Let me start with a simple
example and explain you
how things happen
at a conceptual level.
Let us try and understand
how you recognize a square
from other shapes.
The first thing
you do is you check
whether there are four lines
associated with a figure
or not simple concept, right?
If yes, we further check
if they are connected
and closed again a few years.
We finally check
whether it is perpendicular
and all its sides are equal,
correct, if Fulfills.
Yes, it is a square.
Well, it is nothing but
a nested hierarchy of Concepts
what we did here we
took a complex task
of identifying a square
and this case and broken
into simpler tasks.
Now this deep learning
also does the same thing
but at a larger scale,
let's take an example
of machine which recognizes
the animal the task
of the machine is to recognize
whether the given image is
of a cat or a dog.
What if we were asked to resolve
the same issue using the concept
of machine learning
what we would do first.
We would Define
the features such as
check whether the animal has
whiskers are not a check
if the animal has pointed ears
or not or whether its tail
is straight or curved in short.
We will Define
the facial features and let
the system identify which
features are more important
in classifying a
particular animal now
when it comes to deep learning
it takes this to one step ahead
deep learning automatically
finds out the feature
which are most important
for classification compare
into machine learning
where we Had to manually give
out that features by now.
I guess you have understood
that AI is a bigger picture
and machine learning
and deep learning or it's apart.
So let's move on
and focus our discussion
on machine learning
and deep learning the easiest
way to understand the difference
between the machine learning
and deep learning is to know
that deep learning is machine
learning more specifically.
It is the next evolution
of machine learning.
Let's take few
important parameter
and compare machine learning
with deep learning.
So starting with
data dependencies,
the most important difference
between deep learning
and machine learning is
its performance as the volume
of the data gets increased
from the below graph.
You can see that
when the size of the data
is small deep learning algorithm
doesn't perform that well,
but why well,
this is because deep
learning algorithm needs
a large amount of data
to understand it perfectly
on the other hand
the machine learning
algorithm can easily work
with smaller data set fine.
Next comes the hardware
dependencies deep learning.
Are heavily dependent
on high-end machines
while the machine
learning algorithm can work
on low and machines as well.
This is because the requirement
of deep learning
algorithm include gpus
which is an integral part
of its working the Deep learning
algorithm requires gpus
as they do
a large amount of matrix
multiplication operations,
and these operations
can only be efficiently
optimized using a GPU
as it is built for this purpose.
Only our third parameter
will be feature engineering well
feature engineering is a process
of putting the domain knowledge
to reduce the complexity
of the data
and make patterns more visible
to learning algorithms.
This process is difficult
and expensive in terms of time
and expertise in case
of machine learning.
Most of the features are needed
to be identified by an expert
and then hand coded
as per the domain
and the data type.
For example, the features
can be a pixel value shapes
texture position orientation
or anything fine the Performance
of most of the machine
learning algorithm depends
on how accurately
the features are identified
and extracted
whereas in case
of deep learning algorithms
it try to learn high
level features from the data.
This is a very distinctive part
of deep learning
which makes it way ahead
of traditional machine learning
deep learning reduces the task
of developing new feature
extractor for every problem
like in the case of CN
n algorithm it first try
to learn the low-level features
of the image such as
edges and lines
and then it proceeds
to the parts of faces of people
and then finally to
the high-level representation
of the face.
I hope that things
are getting clearer to you.
So let's move on ahead and see
the next parameter.
So our next parameter is
problem solving approach
when we are solving
a problem using traditional
machine learning algorithm.
It is generally recommended
that we first break
down the problem
into different sub parts
solve them individually
and then finally combine them
to get the desired result.
This is how the machine learning
algorithm handles the L'm
on the other hand
the Deep learning algorithm
solves the problem
from end to end.
Let's take an example
to understand this suppose.
You have a task
of multiple object detection.
And your task is to identify.
What is the object and where it
is present in the image.
So, let's see and compare.
How will you tackle
this issue using the concept
of machine learning
and deep learning starting
with machine learning
in a typical machine
learning approach.
You would first divide
the problem into two step
first object detection
and then object recognization.
First of all,
you would use a bounding
box detection algorithm
like grab cut for example
to scan through the image
and find out all
the possible objects.
Now, once the objects
are recognized you would use
object recognization algorithm
like svm with hog
to recognize relevant objects.
Now, finally,
when you combine the result
you would be able to identify.
What is the object
and where it is present
in the image on the other hand
in deep learning approach you
would do Process from end to end
for example in a euro net
which is a type
of deep learning algorithm.
You would pass an image
and it would give out
the location along
with the name of the object.
Now, let's move
on to our fifth comparison
parameter its execution time.
Usually a deep learning
algorithm takes a long time
to train this is
because there's so
many parameter in
a deep learning algorithm
that makes the training longer
than usual the training
might even last for two weeks
or more than that.
If you are training
completely from the scratch,
whereas in the case of machine
learning it relatively takes
much less time to train ranging
from a few weeks to few Arts.
Now, the execution time
is completely reversed
when it comes to the testing
of data during testing
the Deep learning algorithm
takes much less time to run.
Whereas if you compare it
with a KNN algorithm,
which is a type of machine
learning algorithm the test
time increases as the size
of the data increase last
but not the least we
have interpretability as
a factor for comparison
of machine learning
and Running this fact
is the main reason why
deep learning is still
thought ten times
before anyone uses
it in the industry.
Let's take an example suppose.
We use deep learning to give
automated scoring two essays
the performance it gives
and scoring is quite excellent
and is near
to the human performance,
but there's an issue with it.
It does not reveal white
has given that score
indeed mathematically.
It is possible to find out
that which node of a deep
neural network were activated
but we don't know
what the neurons
are supposed to model
and what these layers of neuron
we're doing collectively.
So if able to interpret
the result on the other
hand machine learning algorithm,
like decision tree gives us
a crisp rule for void chose
and watered chose.
So it is particularly easy
to interpret the reasoning
behind therefore the algorithms
like decision tree
and linear or logistic
regression are primarily used in
industry for interpretability.
Before we end this session.
Let me summarize things
for you machine learning uses
algorithm to parse the data
learn from the data
and make informed decision based
on what it has learned fine.
Now this deep learning
structures algorithms
in layers to create
artificial neural network
that can learn
and make Intelligent Decisions
on their own finally
deep learning is a subfield
of machine learning
while both fall
under the broad category
of artificial intelligence
deep learning is usually
what's behind
the most human-like
artificial intelligence.
Well, this was all
for today's discussion
in case you have any doubt
feel free to add your query
to the comment section.
Thank you.
I hope you have enjoyed
listening to this video.
Please be kind enough to like it
and you can comment any
of your doubts and queries
and we will reply them
at the earliest do look out
for more videos in our playlist
And subscribe to Edureka
channel to learn more.
Happy learning.