we hear a lot about how artificial
intelligence and machine learning are
going to change the world and how the
internet of things will make everyone's
life easier but what's the one thing
that underpins all of these
revolutionary Technologies the answer is
data from social media to the iot
devices we're generating immeasurable
amount of data consider the cab service
provider Uber I'm sure all of you have
used Uber what do you think makes Uber a
multi-billion dollar worth company is it
that availability of cabs or is it their
service well the answer is data data
makes them very rich but wait is data
enough to grow a business of course it
isn't you must know how to use the data
to draw useful insights and solve
problems this is where data science
comes in in simple words data science is
the process of using data to find
Solutions or to predict out comes for a
problem statement to better understand
data science let's see how it affects
our day-to-day activities it's a Monday
morning and I have to get to office
before my meeting starts so I quickly
open up Uber and look for cabs but
there's something unusual the cab rates
are comparatively higher at this hour of
the day why does this happen well
obviously because Monday mornings are
peak hours and everyone is rushing off
to work the high demand for cabs leads
to increase in the cab fares we all know
this but how is all of this implemented
data science is at the heart of Uber's
pricing algorithm The Surge pricing
algorithm ensures that their passengers
always get a ride when they need one
even if it comes at the cost of inflated
prices Uber implements data science to
find out which neighborhoods will be the
busiest so that it can activate search
pricing to get more drivers on the road
in this manner Uber maximizes the number
of rides it can provide and hence
benefit from this Uber search pricing
algorithm uses data science let's see
how a data science process always begins
with understanding the business
requirement or the problem you're trying
to solve in this case the business
requirement is to build a dynamic
pricing model that takes effect when a
lot of people in the same area are
requesting rides at the same time this
is followed by data collection Uber
collects data such as the weather
historical data holidays time traffic
pickup and drop location and it keeps a
track of all of this the next stage is
data cleaning well sometimes unnecessary
data is collected such data only
increases the complexity of the problem
an example is Uber might collect
information like the location of
restaurants and cafes nearby now such
data is not needed to analyze Uber
search pricing therefore such data has
to be removed at this step data cleaning
is followed by data exploration and
Analysis the data exploration stage is
like the brain storming of data analysis
this is where you understand the
patterns in your data this is followed
by data modeling the data modeling stage
basically includes building a machine
learning model that predicts the Uber
search at a given time and location this
model is built by using all the insights
and Trends collected in the exploration
stage the model is trained by feeding a
thousands of customer records so that it
can learn to predict the outcome more
precisely next is the data validation
stage now here the model is tested when
a new customer books a ride the data of
the new booking is compared with the
historic data in order to check if there
are any anomalies in the search prices
or any false predictions if any such
anomalies are detected a notification is
immediately sent to the data scientists
at Uber who fix the issue this is how
Uber predicts the search price for a
given location and time the final stage
of data science is deployment and
optimization so after testing the model
and improving its efficiency it is
deployed on all the users at this stage
customer feed back is received and if
there are any issues they are fixed here
so that was the entire data science
process now let's look at a few other
applications of data science data
science is implemented in e-commerce
platforms like Amazon and Flipkart it is
also the logic behind Netflix's
recommendation system now when all
actuality data science has made
remarkable changes in today's market its
applications range from credit card
fraud detection to self-driving cars and
virtual assistants such as Siri and
Alexa let's consider an example suppose
you look for shoes on Amazon but you do
not buy it then and there now the next
day you're watching videos on YouTube
and suddenly you see an ad for the same
item you switch to Facebook there also
you see the same ad so how does this
happen well this happens because Google
Tracks your search history and
recommends ads based on your search
history this is one of the coolest
applications of data science in fact 35
five percent of Amazon's revenue is
generated by product recommendation and
the logic behind product recommendation
is data science let me tell you another
such story Scott Killen never imagined
his Apple watch might save his life but
that's exactly what happened a few
months ago when he had a heart attack in
the middle of the night but how could a
watch detect a heart attack any guesses
well it's data science again Apple used
data science to build a watch that
monitors an individual's Health this
watch collects data such as the person's
heart rate sleep cycle breathing rate
activity level blood pressure Etc and
keeps a record of these measures 24 bar
7. this collected data is then processed
and analyzed to build a model that
predicts the risk of a heart attack so
these were a few applications now the
question is how and why you should
become a data scientist according to
linkedin's March 2019 survey a data
science scientist is the most promising
job role in the US and it stands at
number one on glassdoor's best jobs of
2019. here are a couple of job trends
that I collected from LinkedIn top
companies like Microsoft IBM Facebook
and Google have over thousand job
vacancies and this number is only going
to grow similarly these job Trends show
the vacancy of jobs with respect to
geography coming to the salary of a data
scientist the average salary ranges
between a hundred thousand dollars to
hundred and eighty two thousand dollars
now remember that your salary varies on
your skills your level of experience
your geography and the company you're
working for here are the skills that are
needed to become a data scientist you
must be skilled in statistics expertise
in programming languages like R and
python is a must you're required to have
a good understanding of processes like
data extraction processing wrangling and
exploration you must also be well versed
with the different types of machine
learning algorithms and how they work
Advanced machine learning Concepts like
deep learning is also needed you must
also possess a good understanding of the
different big data processing Frameworks
like Hadoop and Spark and finally you
must know how to visualize the data by
using tools like Tableau and power bi
now that you know what it takes to
become a data scientist it's time to
buckle up and kick start your career as
a data scientist that's all from my side
guys if you wish to learn more about
such trending Technologies make sure you
subscribe to our Channel until next time
happy learning