good afternoon good evening everyone I
hope that all of you are doing well and
doing great first of all thanks for
taking all the time before we start with
anything let me introduce myself my name
is
years of experience in the same field
and uh without wasting any time let's
just get started and let's take a look
at the today's agenda so today's agenda
is what is Big Data what is AWS and big
data in AWS how AWS generally can solve
the Big Data challenges now moving on
now talking about what is Big Data
so big data is a term for collection of
data sets so large and complex that it
becomes difficult to process using on
and database system tools or traditional
data processing applications now we have
five V's of Big Data first is
volume because like by 2020 accumulated
data Universe of data will grow from 4.4
zettabytes to uh to around 44 zettabytes
or or 44 trillion gigabytes because our
data is increasing and since we are
storing a lot of data and since we are
upgrading operating system the files is
changing in getting a huge requirement
right now the next Vector is variety
basically we have different kind of data
which is being generated from different
sources like you can see we have
structured data relational
semi-structured unstructured we have so
many types of different data so we have
a big requirement we have where we have
different type of data as per the
different use cases and we have to
accumulate and we have to work on that
data next is velocity so what is it
basically it means that like we require
there are some special cases of data
that we need in real time like we can't
even expect a delay of that single
second so like for example in every 60
seconds we have more than 100 000 plus
tweets which is getting available in
every 60 seconds we have 1800 TB of data
which is being stored so we need them
need a solution which can be very fast
like the moment you're going to hit that
data is stored updated and the result is
being presented to you so we need a
basically a very super fast way that's
something we manage uh here with the
help of velocity next is basically value
which is the way to bring the correct
meaning out of a data because uh your
Computing the standard language is zero
and one like we are I'm communicating
with you in English you are
understanding that language but if I
talk about your computer system it
understands the language of zero and one
so we need to have our values that your
computer can understand effectively it
is not requiring um so many translators
so many processes to process it should
be fast enough and last is velocity so
which basically says uncertainty and
inconsistency in the data like you can
see in the form of question mark it
needs to be corrected and it needs to be
removed now what is AWS AWS stands for
Amazon web services now AWS is a secure
Cloud platform offering compute power
database storage content delivery and
other functionality to help business
scale and grow now if I talk about what
is the use of cloud now if I ask from
you guys what is a cloud cloud is
basically you know collection of
computing resources which is your power
supply hardware that you get access from
anywhere now for example I have to build
a let's say windows 2019 operating
system I'm going to build on a computer
and I have to take their computer
everywhere with me you know it can be a
desktop it can be a laptop I'm going to
have it Hardware requirement everywhere
now in the case of cloud what we can do
is I can build it on the cloud system
and I can easily access it from
everywhere so that is one of the biggest
benefit that we have that wherever we
have the bulk of data which we need to
access from everywhere that data can be
accessed managed and manipulated uh very
easily so that's the advantage of cloud
like I'm going to create a virtual
machine I can create in seconds and I
can access it from everywhere now
talking about big data in AWS now before
I talk about that as well AWS is a cloud
platform cloud service which is given by
Azure now we have the cloud service
which is given by Microsoft which is
known as Microsoft Azure which is
basically the cloud service from
Microsoft Azure likewise AWS is the name
of a cloud service from Amazon likewise
we have the cloud storage from Google
which is known as gcp Google Cloud
platform navigation big data and AWS you
have the ews plus you have a different
form of data that you combine and you
can manage easily here
now talking about structured learning in
Eureka if you are highly interested to
learn the entire course end to end in
detail uh this is the way we are going
to proceed in the very first class
you're going to understand what is Big
Data and what is going to do uh with the
critical Hands-On in the second class
you will learn about Hadoop architecture
and hdfs with the Practical Hands-On in
the third class you will learn about
Hadoop map reduce framework with the
Hands-On in the fourth class we will
learn about what is Advanced Hadoop
mapreduce it's component core components
with the Hands-On in the fifth class you
will learn about Apache big with the
Hands-On in the sixth class we will
learn about Apache Hive with the
Hands-On in the seventh class we will
learn about Advanced Apache hype and
Edge base to the Hands-On in the eighth
class we will learn about Advanced
Apache HBS with a Hands-On in a ninth
class we will learn about processing
distributed data with Apache spark with
the Hands-On and the 10th class we will
learn about Oz and Hadoop project with
the Practical handsome and at the end
you are going to become a superhero who
is going to have a cape like this just
kidding you are going to become a
superhero with the knowledge now talking
about how exactly your AWS can solve the
problem so basically we have the big
data challenges so many Big Data
challenges that we have how basically
you know AWS can solve those challenges
out now let's take a look so one of the
biggest challenge that we basically get
is data ingestion because our data
injection uh this is the biggest
challenge that we get like how we are
going to ingest the data how we can
manage the data everything so that's the
biggest problem which we get like for
example if I'm bringing different type
of data into a single file structure and
structured it is very difficult for you
to manage that's the biggest problem
second problem that we have is which is
data storage now we are going to have a
bulk of data So eventually we are going
to run out of a space at some point of
time so how I can store different type
of data third is data preprocessing so
data preprocessing basically is one of
the way where the data is going to be
processed right now and uh we want to
let's say use this data in different
applications how we will be able to use
it and the last one is data
visualization now which is the biggest
Factor the people who are the management
they need a real-time course and all so
how easily we can have that data you
know visualization how basically we can
create a report and how basically we can
manage it so how can we do this now
let's take a look first is basically for
data ingestion problem we have a feature
of Amazon finances
we can easily manage it out now for data
preprocessing we basically have Amazon
EMR Amazon redshift with real process we
can easily manage it for data storage we
basically have Amazon S3 and Amazon to
the help of which we can easily manage
it and for the last data visualization
we have the quick Insight now all these
are itself it basically is a bigger
module so this is not like that it's a
smaller module in itself this is the one
of the biggest module like for example
just for quick side I can have a couple
of hours of discussion Amazon history I
can have a couple of hours for
discussion so here this we are telling
the higher level over here because this
is in terms of it but if you want to uh
you know learn everything in detail you
can enroll for the cards where we
covered each and everything in detail
okay so you can wrap up the session for
today thank you so much