react and react native are among the
most popular Technologies used to create
various types of applications
owing to the fact that they are
developed by the same company react and
react native are very much similar yet
different from each other
so hey guys welcome back to a whole new
session from edureka my name is vajiha
and in today's session we're going to
differentiate between react and react
native
we'll start the session by understanding
what is react and the features of react
then we shall take a look at a react
native and its features finally we'll do
a head-to-head comparison between react
and react native okay so without any
further delays let's move on what
exactly is react react is a JavaScript
library that is used to build user
interface for web applications react.js
was developed by Jordan walk a software
engineer working at Facebook
Facebook implemented react.js in 2011 in
its news feed section but it was
released to the public on May 2013.
after the implementation of react
Facebook's UI underwent drastic
improvement
this resulted in satisfied users and a
sudden boost in its popularity not just
that react is also used in other
Facebook applications such as WhatsApp
Instagram
Etc popular websites like Netflix Airbnb
Dropbox Etc make use of react to build
their UI it is currently one of the most
popular JavaScript front-end libraries
which has strong foundation and a large
community supporting it stack Overflow
developer survey 2020 shows that react
is is the second most loved web
framework just after asp.net core not
just that react also tops the list of
most Wanted web Frameworks since react
is only a front-end library and not the
whole framework it Deals Only With The
View component of the MVC or the model
view controller architecture in react
everything is a component
consider one Lego house as an entire
application then compare each of the
Lego blocks to the component which acts
as a building block these blocks or
components are integrated together to
build one bigger and dynamic application
the biggest advantage of using
components is that you can change any
component at any point in time without
affecting the rest of the application
this feature is most effective when
implemented with larger and real-time
applications where the data changes
frequently each time any data is added
or updated react automatically updates
the specific component whose state has
actually changed this saves the browser
from the task of reloading the whole
application to reflect the changes
so talking about the features of react
jsx jsx stands for JavaScript XML it is
an XML HTML like syntax used by react
it extends the ecmascript so that XML or
HTML like text can co-exist along with
the JavaScript react code
this syntax is used by the preprocessors
like Babel to transform HTML like text
found in JavaScript files into standard
JavaScript objects with jsx you can go a
step further by again embedding the HTML
code inside the JavaScript this makes
HTML code easy to understand and boosts
JavaScript performance while making our
application robust virtual Dom like an
actual Dom virtual Dom is also a node
tree that lists the elements and their
attributes and content as objects and
their properties reacts render function
creates a node tree out of the react
components then it Updates this tree in
response to the mutations in data model
caused by various actions done either by
the user or byte system virtual Dom
Works in three steps whenever any
underlying data changes the entire UI is
re-rendered in the virtual Dom
representation then the difference
between the previous term representation
and the new one is calculated once the
calculations are done the real Dom will
be updated only with things that have
actually changed this makes our
application much faster and there is no
memory wastage
testability react views can be used as
functions of the state state is an
object which determines how a component
will render and behave thus we can
easily manipulate with the state of
components which we pass to the react
View and take a look at the output and
triggered actions events functions Etc
this makes react applications quite easy
to test and debug
server side rendering server side
rendering allows you to pre-render the
initial state of your react components
at the server site only with SSR the
server's response to the browser becomes
only the HTML of the page which is now
ready to be rendered thus the browser
can now start rendering without having
to wait for all the JavaScript to be
loaded and executed as a result the web
page loads faster here the user will be
able to see the real web page in spite
of react still downloading the
JavaScript creating the virtual Dom
linking events Etc at the back end
one-way data binding unlike other
Frameworks react follows unidirectional
data flow for one-way data binding the
major advantage of one-way data binding
is that throughout the application the
data flows in a single Direction which
gives you a better control over it
because of this application state is
contained in specific stores and as a
result rest of the components remained
Loosely coupled this makes our
application more flexible leading to
increased efficiency
Simplicity the use of jsx files makes
the application really simple and easy
to code as well as understand
even though we can use plain JavaScript
here using jsx is easier the acts
component based approach along with
distinct life cycle methods also makes
it simple to learn
okay so now moving on towards react
native react native is a cross-platform
mobile application development framework
react native was also created by
Facebook
it makes use of JavaScript as the base
language over the years JavaScript has
gained immense popularity due to the
ease in learning and widespread usage
if someone is well versed with
JavaScript they can start developing
applications using react native without
wasting much time getting accustomed to
the framework
react native's architecture heavily
relies on JavaScript runtime environment
architecture also known as JavaScript
Bridge
the JavaScript code is compiled into
native code at runtime react native uses
flux architecture from Facebook in short
react native uses JavaScript bridge to
communicate with the native modules
with react native a developer is just
provided with UI rendering and device
access modules for Native features react
native is heavily dependent on
third-party libraries and modules so
coming towards the features of react
native write ones and use everywhere
this is react native's base feature it
means that the code written in react
native can be used on any of the mobile
platforms to build native applications
or applications that work on multiple
platforms
language as mentioned earlier react
native makes use of JavaScript which is
one of the most popular and widely used
web development languages
for every web developer JavaScript is a
must-have skill what's more this Ultra
essential skill is very easy to learn
and to implement
Community Support when it comes to
Community Support react native surely
has a diverse community that even Hosts
International meetups plugins when you
make use of reacts native you have a
great advantage of adding additional
third-party packages or plugins that you
would like to use in your application
Live reload the live reload feature is
one of the best features that assists
the developer while creating the
application using live reload you will
be able to modify the code as well as
see the modifications simultaneously
testing react native is cost efficient
when it comes to testing it provides a
few unit testing functionalities through
JavaScript Frameworks and snapshot
testing can be done using tools like
jest for other sorts of testing
applications built using react native
heavily depend on third-party
applications so now that you know what
is react and react native and their
features let's move on and see what is
the difference between them so the first
factor that we're going to talk about is
the application types or the usage react
is used to develop web applications
whereas reactinative is used for mobile
application development some examples of
web applications created using react are
Facebook Netflix New York Times Yahoo
mail Etc on the other hand react native
is used in mobile applications such as
Instagram Facebook ads manager Bloomberg
Airbnb ubereats Etc
setup and bundling react native is a
framework of JavaScript and it comes
with all the essentials that you will
need to set up and for the development
of your application react on the other
hand is just a library of JavaScript
therefore when you use react you will
need various other tools for setup and
development
live reload live reload or hot reload as
mentioned earlier is a feature that
allows you to code as well as see the
modifications in your application
simultaneously react native supports
live reload whereas react does not
template rendering both react and react
native use jsx for the development of
views or the templates but react is much
better when it comes to styling your
application's UI using CSS react native
on the other hand makes use of native
platform apis learning curve even though
react is not very difficult to learn
react native is much easier this is
because you can make use of ready-made
components in react native while for
react you will have to coach them
yourself
so we've done a head-to-head comparison
between react and react native the
answer to which one is better among the
two depends on the type of project that
you're creating if you are focusing on
creating the UI for a web application
then react is what you need but if your
project is going to be a mobile
application then you can go with react
native
this brings us to the end of the session
I hope you guys have enjoyed and learned
something new in case you have any
doubts or queries please do let me know
in the comment section and I will reward
to you at the earliest we'll be back
with more and more exciting sessions but
till then goodbye and take care