in this video we are going to learn html
for new developers now if you missed my
last video which is how to set up visual
studio code um in a professional coding
environment and workspace you definitely
want to watch that that link is in the
description go ahead watch that and come
back to here in this video we're going
to learn html which is the content for
the web i'm going to go ahead and close
this real quick i can click on this
folder thing and get rid of all those
files so i have a little more screen to
work with
but if you think about a website it's
got content and it's got look and feel
to it so the content would be the words
on the page any images on the page any
buttons on the page
and that those words images and buttons
could look a thousand different ways
with a thousand different colors so html
is what puts the content on the page um
and it's ugly you can tell that this is
ugly i don't even have a font that's
being chosen for me uh let alone a font
size and a font color or a background
color that's because i'm just using html
right now i'm just adding content to my
page after that we'll get into css which
is cascading style sheets css would say
give me a gray background with blue text
and a button with rounded rectangle
corners on it and let's make this image
small and i don't know let's make it
shake when you hover over it things like
that that's css and so when people learn
html and css together they can build a
full website
and then javascript is what a developer
will learn to add functionality to that
website where you can maybe post a tweet
to twitter and things like that that's
all functionality that's javascript so
those three technologies make a web
developer's tool kit now what we're
going to do in this video is we're going
to learn html
and html is the easiest piece of all
three you can really learn it in a day
or even an hour because all you have to
do is memorize a few words let me show
you what i mean here i'm going to take
away all this code
and i'm going to leave that top one
there because that's the one that says
hey it's an html web page
everything in html is considered a tag a
tag looks like this a greater than
symbol the tag name we'll call this html
and then any attributes i'll get to
attributes in a second and then the less
than symbol you can see when i type that
less than symbol vs code visual studio
code automatically added what's called a
closing tag for me which is the same
thing but it has a slash anything
between the opening tag and the closing
tag is considered inside of a tag so if
i type type type type this is now inside
of my html tag and that's how that works
you can have tags inside of tags i could
have a body inside of the
html tag
and then i could have other tags inside
of that you can have as many tags inside
of as many tags as you want it's all
just tags tags can be two things they
can have an opening closing
or if there's nothing inside of them
they can be what's called self-closing
which you add a slash to the end of it
and a good example of this would be an
image an image
is the img tag
and image doesn't have text inside of it
or any of that it loads an image
from a web server and spits it out on
the page so we don't have to have an
opening and closing tag it can be self
closing
and then we define things how does that
image know which image we're pulling
from the internet we're going to use
what's called attributes for that so a
tag can have one or more attributes to
do an attribute you do a space
after the tag name and you give it an
attribute let's say it has a width
width equals 300. and so you do equals
and then an opening closing of
quotes and then whatever's inside of
that is considered the attribute so
think of it as a person right the tag
name is image let's say this was called
frank
and frank has a height well he could
have a width too
there's attributes about frank right as
a person he's got a certain height and
he's got a certain intelligence
these are things that are
qualities about frank intelligence high
and so that's kind of how tags and
attributes work the tag is what the
thing is
the attributes describe
things about that tag so in this case we
have in the case of image we have an
image
and you might have a height a width and
a source which is where that image comes
from that is all of html we just covered
all of html right here tags with tag
names and attributes that's it from here
on out you just have to memorize a few
tag names
and a few attributes and you have all of
html done so let's get into some of
these common tag names there's really
three categories that give you
everything you need to start off to
build an html web page you have to have
three tags to start off you have to have
an html tag again i'm just typing html
and hitting tab here and visual studio
code is doing the rest so really all you
do have to do is memorize some words so
i'm doing an html tag inside of that i'm
going to do a head tag
and then i'm also going to do a body tag
those are the three tags that it takes
to build a web page you notice that head
and body are both inside of html that's
extremely important
now html doesn't care about white space
at all so these could be like this
these could be like that it doesn't
really matter none of that matters it
only matters to you the developer we
like to keep them
indented in such a way where it's easy
to see what's inside of what so that's
what the indentions are all about i
indent using tab so you can go tab and
then you can also select one or more
things and do shift tab or tab and
things will move around indention wise
so that's what those indentions are all
about
in our head tag we'll add one title tag
here and let's say my page
and let's add an exclamation mark
because we're feeling chirpy today so
there we go you can see up here at the
top if you can see it because it's
really little it says my page
exclamation mark in the body let's add
our hello world back
and then that is our web page so we've
got our body our body is everything that
the user sees in this main body of the
web page so all of the rest of our tags
are going to go in here
and so that is your basic three tags for
a web page html head body and a title
tag which you don't have to do but
pretty much everybody wants to do it
because you want your tab to have a
title so now let's look into how you
style text text comes with
h1 tag being your biggest piece of text
which is a header
there you go wow that's really big i'm
kind of zoomed in here to make it easier
but wow that h1 is big and you can go
all the way down to h6
my subtitle
so you notice that h2 is by default a
little smaller the default css for h1 is
going to make it huge and h2 is going to
be smaller and smaller still all the way
down to h6 i'll do an h6 here which is
even smaller
so the h6 is even smaller than and what
these are used for is these are used for
telling google
if you want it to rank your page to rank
on google and all of the web browsers
and everything what the most important
pieces of your page are so google is
going to look at your page and it's
going to say oh the h1 that's the title
for the whole page h2 these are section
subtitles so any
content blocks within your page will be
h2s and farther down if if an h2 has
multiple content blocks in that those
will all be h3s that's what we use those
tags for css could make this one huge
and make this one tiny so it doesn't
necessarily relate to size it more
relates to importance so those are our
h1 h2 those are our header tags
and then there's a p tag which is for a
paragraph hi i'm
a paragraph of text
so there's my paragraph of text and if i
do multiple ones of these
then you'll notice that each one kind of
has a space in between it just like you
would expect a paragraph to do default
css is going to add a space below each
paragraph
and so that's how paragraphs work now
you'll remember i mentioned that html
does not care about white space so if i
do a ton of spaces here it doesn't
change when i save it nothing is
different what if i add a million
returns here well accidentally got a
slash so we'll get rid of that slash if
i had a million returns nothing changes
html does not care about spaces past one
the first space works because you know
you really couldn't type anything
without a space
but that's kind of how html works it
doesn't care about white space white
space is what you use as the developer
to make it easy to read all the content
well what if i wanted to add a line
break like that well there's an actual
tag for a line break called br and it's
a self-closing tag because it doesn't
have any content in it and you can see
there we go we have an actual line break
a return an enter key got added into
that so that's a tag you want to know as
well br for line break
and then what if you want to change some
of the ways these work
you can add strong to make it bold
let's make it a strong paragraph added a
space there probably don't need a space
there strong is basically what you use
for bold if you're looking at really old
web pages you may see a b tag floating
around which does the same thing but
that's that shouldn't be used anymore
strong is what you should use for bold
now
and then em is what you use for emphasis
which is italics you can see there we go
italics so those are the tags that we
use for bold and italics strong and em
and we're actually getting a lot of the
way through this list so if you feel
overwhelmed just remember we only have
about 12 words we have to memorize html
head title body
p
strong em
and then we also covered our header tags
and you're almost through basic html
with just those words uh here's a fun
one there's buttons i'm a button
there we go we have a button looks like
i got a typo in there somewhere yep got
an extra little piece
and you can click it
we have a button there no style to it
but there's a button on the page and the
button also doesn't do anything because
we don't have any javascript or anything
telling the button what to do but hey
the button is there all the same so
that's all of our text tags i'm going to
show you two more tags and then we're
done with basic html we can actually
start learning basic css from here on
out so let's go and add a list tag these
are actually really important so if i go
li
and say i'm an item
you can see i kind of have a bulleted
list right there yep i have a bulleted
list
and if i have multiple items i could
either lay them out like that or i
should if i have multiple items wrap
them in a ul which is unordered list and
now i have to select this and cut it and
paste it because i did it in a weird
order and you learned to get really good
at those kind of things as a web
developer so i have a ul tag
with multiple li tags in it this is an
unordered list and list items so that's
what those stand for these would be
things like a navigation a top
navigation on your page you will define
a list of things and then use css to lay
them out as a navigation
you can also change this to o l
o l
and you'll make it an ordered list which
is not very useful you don't do this as
often in html but you can see as soon as
i changed it to ol i got number one
number two added to my lis but usually
li and ul is the combination you'll go
for that creates a list of items and
then you can use css to style that in a
way you need to so there you go that's
it that's all you need to know for html
it's tags with attributes with tag names
that's html in a nutshell let's start
building an actual web page with style
and look and feel in the next video
we're going to get into css
you