hey guys how's it going i'm back here
with another video and today i decided
to bring this video which is going to be
the first video of a new series i'm
going to bring here to the channel um
for the longest time i've been wanting
to release some sort of
beginners to advanced course in react
especially because my channel is all
based in react however i was really
wondering if i was going to release it
as a paid course or
just as videos on youtube and for a very
long time i was preparing to release it
as a paid course however i realized that
it doesn't really make sense for me to
release it as a big course because i
personally don't even use courses never
used it in the past and also i feel like
i can benefit more from releasing it for
free on youtube because i'll be able to
grow more of my audience and i'll be
able to provide this for free for you
guys as well so what i decided to do is
i decided to release this course where
i'm going to be going over everything in
react right from the beginning
right from setting up the react
application to working with more complex
projects and more complex topics my goal
is that by the end of this course um you
will be able to confidently create a
react application and work in it on your
own and not only that but also if you
have any doubts you will be able to
search on the internet to solve whatever
doubts you have no one truly knows
everything from a language or a
framework but if you're skilled enough
and prepared and you have practiced
enough on a certain topic you can
basically tell yourself that you know
that because you're able to search and
resolve problems on your own and that's
my goal with this course i'm not
completely sure how many videos this
course will um
will be composed of i have a list of all
the topics we're going to be going over
but um keep in mind that if you guys are
keep suggesting me stuff that you guys
want to learn throughout the way i might
change this list by the end so the
topics that we're going to be um
learning in this course are probably
showing here in the screen right now um
as i mentioned uh some of them might
change i might add more stuff i might
remove some stuff but those are the ones
that i i really want to teach because i
feel like those are the really important
ones that will set you up for the future
throughout the course i'll also be
pointing out other videos that i have
made in the past because i have already
made really in-depth tutorials on some
of these topics so if you're interested
in checking those out as well i'll just
link to them in the video so you can go
ahead and watch them as well now i've
been releasing videos about once or
twice a week but because i don't want to
keep you guys waiting like weeks for
this course to be done um i'll try to
post
as much as possible um probably three
plus videos a week um also those v this
videos won't take that long to make
there won't be that long so
i'll try to keep them short in order for
me to be able to post as much as i can
i'm really excited for this course i
really hope it is the best that i can
provide for you guys and um yeah if you
have any any suggestions on what you
want to learn just leave it in the
comment and um for this first video what
we're going to be going over is just the
basics of react um going over why we
should use react why would you want to
learn react um and also i'm going to
show you guys how to set up your first
react application so with that in mind
let's get into the first video of this
course
[Music]
[Applause]
okay everyone so the first thing i want
to go over is why exactly you should
learn react now this is a kind of a
trivial question because if you're
watching these videos um you're probably
already know why you would want to learn
react however you got to understand
exactly why it is required for you to
learn react um in order to improve as a
developer or a web developer more
specifically now the reason why i'm
saying this is because i remember in the
beginning i was really used to just
coding websites using vanilla javascript
or some really outdated frameworks such
as jquery and when i started learning
react i was wondering to myself why am i
wasting time learning this when i kind
of when i can do all of this using some
sort of outdated method and that really
stunted my my growth uh for a bit it
definitely made it so that i took a
little bit longer than um than usual to
learn the basics of react and for that
reason i wanted to start out by just
explaining to you guys why you should
actually learn react now the first thing
i want to say is that you will love
react i'll be honest if this is the
first framework you're learning i'm not
saying
react is perfect but i'm just saying if
this is the first time you're learning a
framework and you're coming from just
knowing vanilla javascript and coding
websites without using any of the
available frameworks out there um i'm
gonna let you know that you might not
like it in the beginning but you will
love it after a while the the the way in
which using a framework um abstracts
complexity in your project is is really
nice i i love it as soon as i realized
um how much less code i had to write in
order to make a complex website compared
to something like using normal
javascript i i really fell in love with
using something like react now like i
mentioned react is not the perfect
framework at all it is an open source
library created by facebook and
maintained by a facebook group which
constantly deals with
backlash and opinions from other people
on how certain things should be handled
react is constantly updating and
constantly being maintained which is
really nice and has a massive community
around it everyone knows that react
dominates the the javascript um
framework library
industry right and the reason for it is
because react right in the beginning
when it started to be created it came up
with a concept called the virtual dom
which um was pretty new at the time you
see angular which is another framework
um
copied or got inspired by this this
concept but i feel like react did it in
a better way and was already getting
more popular by the time that angular
released its new version now react
changed a lot throughout the years you
might go to youtube and watch a tutorial
from 2018 and see code that is
completely different from what it is
right now so it is important for you to
recognize that the date in which you're
watching your tutorials is really
important now most companies out there
will be using react or some sort of
alternative to react that is based on
react such as next.js for example um and
that's from my opinion already a really
a pretty good reason for you to start
learning it because if it is a standard
in the industry um and you're gonna be
working on the industry you better be
aligned with what people are using and
you'll have a much easier time finding a
job if you know something that is way
more popular a lot of the big companies
out there are using react in some sort
of part of the application and um it is
important for you to understand that
it's not only how the framework or
library performs that makes it good um
the community and the the amount of
people who embraces that project
definitely plays a role in it and react
definitely wins in that specific case
now it's hard for me to talk specific
things about why you should use react
because you haven't probably used react
in the past so explaining stuff that are
more technical is pretty hard so i'm
gonna be mentioning this kind of stuff
throughout the course um just so you
guys can refer to that in the beginning
but for now just understand that react
is widely used in the world it is it
will make your life way easier when you
start building anything which is a
little bit more complicated than a than
a medium project and um
it will make your life easier in the
long run so that's why i think you
should be learning react now i want to
go over uh some of the stuff that i'm
expecting you to know before we get into
the course um so these are the kind of
stuff that i will gloss over or not
explain much because
um
it's assumed that you already know in
order to start learning this course now
what i'm assuming is that you already
know html and css now i'm also assuming
that you know a little bit of javascript
i personally didn't learn um javascript
before react i knew the basics like
really basic stuff but i wasn't good at
it at all so for that reason i am
assuming you know html css and the
basics of javascript um because if you
don't um it will make learning the score
discourse a little bit difficult um
however i will still be going over some
javascript stuff like um some functions
that we're gonna be consistently using
um some different methods and concepts
that are important so if this isn't you
and you don't know the stuff that is
required for this course i recommend
just working a little bit before you
actually start watching the videos so
now that i went over all of this stuff
that i really wanted to talk about let's
start with actually working with our
first piece of code what we're going to
be doing is we're just going to start by
setting up a react application um inside
of our computer and um just looking at
how the project looks so let's get into
it so let's get started on setting up
our first react application i want to
start off by saying that the code for
every episode in this whole course will
be in the description so if you want to
go to the code for a specific episode
you can just go to the link in the
description or you go to the original
repository on github and just move
throughout the different branches that
i'm going to create um for this project
or this whole course so what we need to
do in order to set up our first react
application is make sure that we first
have a code editor to work with i a
hundred a thousand percent recommend
using vs code it is pretty much a
standard in the industry and i've tried
a bunch of editors this one is the best
one um so i would definitely recommend
using it
also you need to make sure that you have
both npm which is uh
one of the most famous package manager
out there you want to have it installed
it doesn't have to be this specific
version this is just the one that i'm
using and you also need to have node.js
installed so
or node installed right so you can see i
have both of them installed into my
computer so those are the two things
that are necessary for you to actually
create your first react application
now in order to create your application
you need to open up a project a folder
inside of your vs code so what i did is
i just opened over here as you can see i
have a folder called
episode one and i just opened it up
inside of my vs code um
like app
and inside of the terminal over here uh
what i want to do is i just want to run
the command npx
create
react
app like this now what this does is the
create react app will generate a bowler
play code for
a very basic react application and we
can specify um where we want to create
this application by putting for example
the name of the folder where our app
will be created right so if i i had a i
was creating for example a social media
website i could create put over here
social media website
and what would happen is it would create
a react application and would also
create a folder called social media
website and put the create react
application inside of that folder in our
case we want to create the react
application inside of the folder we are
already inside which is the episode one
so what we can do in that case is just
put a dot it doesn't matter what way you
do it
you can do it both ways i'm going to do
it this way so that when i press enter
you'll see that it will start generating
our application and it will generate the
files inside of the the folder we are
currently inside
so it will start um running all of these
commands um and it won't take a while it
actually doesn't take it takes less than
a minute but i'll be back in a second
when this is done okay as you can see um
it just finished everything you'll
you'll notice it finished because at the
end it will say happy hacking and that's
the the signal that you have that
everything was installed um correctly
we're gonna clear it up and just close
our terminal and you can see we have a
bunch of different folders and files
over here on our left i'm going to go
over each one of them and explain to you
guys what they mean so basically we
first have a readme which is just
something for
github for example uh you i would just
ignore it for now
we also have the git ignore which is
also something for github i would also
just ignore it
then we have our package.json and our
package lock.json so this comes when you
install any packages using npn
package.json is just a json file which
contains information about your project
and also about all the dependencies that
you have installed in your application
so
our project as you can see by default
its name is episode one because it's the
name of the folder you can obviously
change all of this this is more for
documentation purposes um because for
example if you were to
create or clone this application
you can just look at all the
dependencies which are just extra
packages and libraries you install in
your project to then know what you need
to install in your own project so you
can see we have already with the command
installed the react library and the
react dom library together with all of
the other stuff that comes with this
comment
now all this stuff over here they're
meant to
i wouldn't worry about them for now uh
we will go over all of this later but
for now let's just keep it like this
just understand that this is
mainly for documentation purposes
then i'm also going to ignore the
package.json because it really doesn't
matter for now
and also the node modules because most
of you guys might know this is just a
folder containing all the packages and
libraries you installed
so we have over here by default in a
react application our public and our
source folder our public folder is just
containing a bunch of um
kind of static files right so we have an
a bunch of pictures by default like
logos that come with the bowler play
code we also have a bunch of text files
and json files and also importantly an
html file now why do we have an html
file over here when we are working with
a react application we're not going to
be creating html files this is something
that is really important to understand
because react provides us with a method
of creating an application which is a
single page application and what does
that mean exactly it means that our
whole app will exist instead of one
single html file which is the index.html
so what happens is inside of this file
over here we're going to have a div as
you can see over here a single div with
an id of root and what react does is
when you are when you enter in the
website react will grab all the code you
write all the react code you write
with javascript and just put everything
inside of this div now why is this good
well there's benefits and there's
negatives to it one benefit is that you
will not need to be downloading more
files as you move in your application if
you just have multiple html files for
each page of your app you need to
download that html file every single
time you move on your app
but with react that's different
everything is downloaded before and you
don't need to download and anything more
when you're navigating right so this is
important to understand because we're
not going to be creating html files but
rather our whole app will exist inside
of javascript files which you can see
over here or typescript files if you're
going to use typescript we're going to
talk about typescript later on inside of
this course
but this is how the source folder
basically
looks like so we have a couple files
over here we have our test files um our
setup tests and we also have a report
webvitas.js
we have a logo which like i mentioned it
just is just coming with the
initial boilerplate code we have an
index.js file a
index.css file um a test an app.test.js
file an app.js file and an app.css file
now i want to run this application right
now before we before i go over those
files and before i do anything so you
guys can see how our app looks using the
create react tab command now in order to
run our first react app i just need to
come over here and i just need to put
npm start now what this is going to do
is this is going to start running our
application into a live server inside of
our browser the server will run on the
local host 3000 so make sure you don't
have anything running on the port 3000
and every time you make any changes into
your code and you save the file it will
automatically refresh and rerun your
application so it shows the changes so
i'm going to press enter over here and
it will start running everything and you
can see on my browser now i am inside of
the host 3000 this is how our project
initially looks like because this is how
it comes with the create react tab
command but we're obviously going to
make a single change into our project so
we can show hello world appearing in our
screen so in order to do that i want to
come over here and i want to go over uh
what the files are right
so some of these files are actually
unnecessary and i won't even go over
them right now and that's important for
me to emphasize because if you try to
understand them now it will just waste
your time because you definitely won't
be using them for a while
in the beginning of your journey for
learning react so i'm going to delete
the setup tests over here the report web
vitals the local.svg
the index.css
the app.task.js and that's basically it
so i'm just going to delete them like
this and now it should be fine
now since we deleted the index.css and
the report web vitals if you recall i
just deleted those files you also have
to delete their import statements from
the index.js so i'm going to delete both
of them and this call over here
and i'm going to save it right now
then i also need to delete the stuff
that we imported in the app.js which is
the logo
and i'm just going to delete all of this
code over here because this is the code
that comes with that makes our website
appear like it was before right now you
see it's just a blank page because we
deleted everything
now what i want to explain to you guys
is that when you have that html file
over there right we have i mentioned to
you guys that we have the single html
file
well inside of the index.js this is
where we create a react like element a
route to all of our code and we put it
inside of the element in the html file
with the id root so you see what it's
doing over here is it's grabbing this
div over here and it's putting all of
our code inside of that div
now what exactly is it putting inside of
that div well it's going to be putting
this thing over here which is known as a
component i'm going to go over
components in the next video but think
about it at this this way all of the
code in your project will initially
exist inside of this app function over
here now i know if this is the first
time you're looking at react you might
think this is lit this looks weird
you're creating a function that returns
what looks like html well don't worry
i'll go over this in the next video but
for now if we want to display hello
world inside of our project all we have
to do is just write hello world over
here save it and if we come to our
google chrome you'll see it says hello
world in our screen so this is basically
it for the first video i really hope you
guys enjoyed it if you enjoyed it please
leave a like down below and comment what
you want to see next i'm really excited
for this course i'm really really
excited for this course i want to i want
to make this as valuable as possible and
i don't want to tailor this just for
beginners just for intermediate or just
for advanced i want to make something
that whenever you have any doubts you
whenever you forget something you just
go back and watch it because each video
can exist not only in in the context of
the two of the series but also in the
context of the topic itself so i want to
have a library of everything you might
want to learn about react inside of my
channel so that's my hope for this
series i hope that you start as a
beginner and you end as good as you can
be so
that's basically it really hope you guys
enjoyed it and i'll see you guys in the
next episode
[Music]
[Applause]